<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on September 01, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00280020</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AG0061</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01AG026364</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00280020</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Behavioral Treatment of Insomnia in Aging</brief_title>
  <official_title>Aging: Cytokine Mechanisms and Treatment of Insomnia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate whether Tai Chi Chih vs. cognitive behavioral
      therapy vs. sleep education reduces insomnia in older adults. The secondary goal of the study
      is to determine whether the behavioral treatment of insomnia alters proinflammatory cytokine
      activity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Insomnia is a prominent complaint in late-life. However, little scientific effort has been
      directed toward identifying the biological mechanisms that are related to abnormal sleep or
      to evaluating the efficacy of behavioral treatments for insomnia in older adults. Basic
      observations demonstrate that proinflammatory cytokines play a key role in the regulation of
      sleep. Previous research shows that cytokines are reciprocally linked with abnormal sleep.
      This trial builds upon these findings and extends a program of study that has examined the
      efficacy of behavioral interventions on health outcomes in the elderly.

      Preliminary studies found that Tai Chi Chih (TCC), a slow moving meditation, contributes to
      improvements in subjective sleep quality, sleep amounts and sleep efficiency, alterations in
      sympathetic activity, decreases in proinflammatory cytokines, and improvements in health
      functioning in community-dwelling older adults. Additionally, cognitive behavior therapy
      (CBT) confers benefits on sleep outcomes.

      In this randomized, controlled trial, 150 older adults will be randomly assigned to CBT, TCC,
      or sleep hygiene/education control (EC) over 16 weeks and followed for one year. The aims of
      this project are to: 1) evaluate the effects of CBT vs TCC vs. EC on objective and subjective
      measures of sleep and on fatigue, mood, and health functioning in older adults with insomnia;
      2) determine the effects of CBT vs.TCC vs. EC on measures of proinflammatory cytokine
      activity and sympathovagal balance, and whether these two biological mechanisms are related
      to changes of disordered sleep over the course of the treatment trial; and 3) evaluate
      whether circulating levels of proinflammatory cytokines are associated with measures of sleep
      continuity in older adults with insomnia over the treatment trial. This study will advance
      psychobiological models of disordered sleep and the potential benefits of two readily
      exportable behavioral interventions for promoting improvements in sleep outcomes in the
      elderly.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in insomnia symptoms as measured by subjective report and objective polysomnography</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjective report: Baseline, 8, 12, 16 weeks, 3 months 1 year; PSG: Baseline, 16 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in measures of proinflammatory cytokine activity.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8, 12, 16 weeks, 3 months 1 year (single samples); repeated blood sampling during PSG nights for circadian cytokine activity: Baseline, 16 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in daytime impairment secondary to insomnia</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8, 12, 16 weeks, 3 months 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in fatigue, depression and mood, and health function</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8, 12, 16 weeks, 3 months 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in sympathovagal function and energy balance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8, 12, 16 weeks, 3 months 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in measures of interpersonal resilience and social</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8, 12, 16 weeks, 3 months 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Allostatic load</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, post-treatment, and one year follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>CBC, glucose, HbA1c, lipids, fibrinogen, measures of inflammation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">123</enrollment>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <condition>Insomnia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CBT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TCC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tai Chi Chih (TCC)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will learn and practice 20 movements in 1 hour sessions twice per week for 16 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>TCC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavior Therapy (CBT)</intervention_name>
    <description>For each 2-hour session held once a week for 16 weeks, the CBT treatment manual will outline objectives, patient skills, and treatment activities. Therapists will direct role-playing and other skill-development exercises that will be designed to increase patients' self-efficacy in managing their insomnia. Homework assignments will be planned weekly to ensure practice and skill application.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CBT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sleep Seminar (SS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Each 2-hour session, held once a week for 16 weeks, consists of a 60-minute video presentation followed by a 60-minute question-and-answer discussion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Older than 55 years of age at time of entry

          -  Sleep-onset delay, maintenance insomnia, or terminal insomnia

          -  Difficulties with sleep for a minimum of 3 nights per week

          -  Insomnia duration of at least 6 months

          -  Complaint of at least 1 negative effect during waking hours (e.g., fatigue, impaired
             functioning, mood disturbances) attributed to insomnia

          -  Habitual sleep-wake schedule reporting &quot;lights-out&quot; between 9:00 PM and midnight

          -  Accessible geographically

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Evidence that insomnia is directly related to a medical disorder (e.g.,
             hyperthyroidism) or effects of a medication that affects sleep structure and/or immune
             functioning

          -  Presence of sleep apnea or periodic limb movements during sleep

          -  Presence of another sleep disorder (e.g., Advanced or Delay Sleep Phase Syndrome)

          -  Regular use of a hypnotic or psychotropic medication (sleeping pills) and/or current
             psychotherapy or other behavioral therapy that would confound CBT or TCC

          -  Current history of a major psychiatric disorder (e.g. current major depression,
             alcohol or substance dependence, anxiety disorder)

          -  Cognitive impairment as suggested by a score lower than 23 on the Mini-Mental State
             examination

          -  Abnormal screening laboratory tests (e.g., abnormal thyroid hormone, elevated TSH,
             positive screening for HIV or hepatitis C)

          -  Smokers will also be excluded because of potential confounding effects on markers of
             inflammation

          -  Body mass index that is greater than 30 kg/m2 as obesity is associated with excessive
             levels of inflammatory markers

          -  Women must be post-menopausal

          -  Unable to commit to intervention schedule
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael R. Irwin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cousins Center for Psychoneuroimmunology, UCLA Neuropsychiatric Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cousins Center for Psychoneuroimmunology, UCLA Neuropsychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irwin M, Pike J, Oxman M. Shingles Immunity and Health Functioning in the Elderly: Tai Chi Chih as a Behavioral Treatment. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med. 2004 Dec;1(3):223-232. Epub 2004 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>15841255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irwin MR, Pike JL, Cole JC, Oxman MN. Effects of a behavioral intervention, Tai Chi Chih, on varicella-zoster virus specific immunity and health functioning in older adults. Psychosom Med. 2003 Sep-Oct;65(5):824-30.</citation>
    <PMID>14508027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Motivala SJ, Sarfatti A, Olmos L, Irwin MR. Inflammatory markers and sleep disturbance in major depression. Psychosom Med. 2005 Mar-Apr;67(2):187-94.</citation>
    <PMID>15784782</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 20, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 9, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 9, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 11, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Irwin, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor in Residence</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>sleep disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>meditation</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive behavior therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sleep Initiation and Maintenance Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

