<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on September 01, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00280007</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MPR-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00280007</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transarterial Chemoembolisation Plus Bevacizumab for Treatment of Hepatocellular Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>AVATACE-1: Bevacizumab (Avastin®) as Inhibitor of Collateral Tumor Vessel Growth During Transarterial Chemoembolisation (TACE) for Hepatocellular Carcinoma (HCC) a Pilot Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Vienna</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with liver cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma will undergo transarterial
      chemoembolisation (TACE) as clinically indicated and will be randomized to receive
      bevacizumab or placebo every 2 weeks up to 1 year. Tumor response will be assessed using MR
      of the liver and PET-scanning.

      It will be tested whether the addition of bevacizumab as angiogenic inhibitor will slow down
      tumor progression, reduce the need for re-embolisation and will improve patient survival.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      TACE is an established therapy for patients with advanced stage HCC not amenable to liver
      transplantation or resection and has been shown to significantly improve survival in these
      patients compared to no treatment (8). TACE takes advantage of the predominantly arterial
      blood supply of malignant liver tumors contrary to the surrounding normal liver tissue, which
      receives more blood supply through the portal venous system.

      TACE leads to predictable tumor necrosis until new blood vessels grow into the tumor margins
      to support tumor growth. Quite often after cutting off the blood supply through the hepatic
      artery, the tumor induces active angiogenesis to promote collateral blood vessel growth from
      liver capsule arteries or collaterals from the gastroduodenal artery. VEGF seems to be an
      important player in inducing this angiogenetic activity and tumor control and survival of
      patients after TACE have been linked to serum VEGF-levels with higher levels showing reduced
      survival.

      Inhibition of these neoangiogenetic activity could lead to significantly improved in tumor
      control and survival in patients with advanced stage HCC.

      2. STUDY OBJECTIVE

        -  to assess the effectiveness of bevacizumab in combination with TACE as measured by
           patients without tumor progression on MRT after 3 cycles of TACE as well as the number
           of TACE cycles applied for recurrent tumor after a maximum of one year treatment with
           bevacizumab

        -  to assess collateral tumor vessel growth on MRT / CT
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Safety concerns in the treatment arm
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>to assess the effectiveness of bevacizumab in combination with TACE as measured by patients without tumor progression after a maximum of one year treatment with bevacizumab</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>to assess collateral tumor vessel growth on MRT / CT after 3, 6, and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>time to progression</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>total number of TACE-cycles applied</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>metabolically active tumor size on PET-scan</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>circulating endothelial progenitors and pro-angiogenic hematopoietic cells as markers of angiogenesis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HGF-levels during therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>portal hypertension and systemic hemodynamics</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cost</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>bevacizumab infusion evey 2 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo infusion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bevacizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>bevacizumab 5 mg/kg i.v. every 14 days for 52 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>-avastin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with histologically confirmed HCC not suitable for OLT or resection (&gt;3
             nodules, &gt;5 cm diameter, vascular invasion, clinically significant portal
             hypertension, other contraindications against OLT) or patients awaiting OLT with an
             expected waiting time &gt;12 months

          -  Child-Pugh Stage A and B

          -  Liver disease of any etiology

          -  Written informed consent (approved by the Institutional Review Board [IRB]/Independent
             Ethics Committee [IEC]) obtained prior to any study specific screening procedures

          -  Patient must be able to comply with the protocol

          -  Age ≥18 years

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test done 1 week
             prior to the administration of the study drug. Fertile women and men of childbearing
             potential (&lt;2 years after last menstruation in women) must use effective means of
             contraception (oral contraceptives, intrauterine contraceptive device, barrier method
             of contraception in conjunction with spermicidal jelly or surgically sterile)

          -  Proteinuria at baseline:

               -  Urine dipstick of proteinuria &lt;2+. Patients discovered to have &gt;2+ proteinuria on
                  dipstick urinalysis at baseline, should undergo a 24-hour urine collection and
                  must demonstrate less &lt;= 1 g of protein/24 hr.

          -  Haematology:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt; 1 x 109/L

               -  Platelet count &gt; 40 x 109/L

               -  Haemoglobin &gt; 9 g/dL (may be transfused to maintain or exceed this level)

               -  Prothrombin time &gt;= 40%

          -  Biochemistry:

               -  Total bilirubin &lt;= 5 mg/dL

               -  Serum creatinine &lt; 3.0 mg/dL

               -  Life expectancy of &gt;3 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  extra hepatic tumor spread

          -  complete portal vein thrombosis (common trunk)

          -  Child-Pugh-Stage C

          -  Prior TACE or TAE

          -  Other experimental therapies for HCC

          -  Acute variceal bleeding within the last 2 weeks

          -  Large oesophageal varices (&gt;5 mm diameter) without prophylactic band ligation

          -  Past or current history (within the last 2 years prior to randomisation) of
             malignancies except for the indication under this study and curatively treated basal
             and squamous cell carcinoma of the skin or in situ carcinoma of the cervix

          -  History or evidence upon physical examination of CNS disease unless adequately treated
             (e.g., seizure not controlled with standard medical therapy or history of stroke
             within &lt; 6 months), excluding hepatic encephalopathy

          -  Major surgical procedure, open biopsy, or significant traumatic injury within 28 days
             prior to study treatment start, or anticipation of the need for major surgical
             procedure during the course of the study

          -  Current or recent (within 10 days prior to study treatment start) use of full-dose
             oral or parenteral anticoagulants for therapeutic purposes

          -  Chronic, daily treatment with aspirin (&gt;325mg/day)

          -  Pregnancy (positive serum pregnancy test) or lactation

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension

          -  Serious, non-healing wound, ulcer, or bone fracture

          -  Patients with known allergy to Chinese hamster ovary cell proteins or other
             recombinant human or humanized antibodies or to any excipients of Bevacizumab
             formulation; or to any other study drugs

          -  Currently or recent (within the 30 days prior to starting study treatment) treatment
             of another investigational drug or participation in another investigational study

          -  Clinically significant (i.e. active) cardiovascular disease for example
             cerebrovascular accidents (≤ 6 months prior to randomisation), myocardial infarction
             (≤ 6 months prior to randomisation), unstable angina, New York Heart Association
             (NYHA) grade II or greater congestive heart failure, serious cardiac arrhythmia
             requiring medication

          -  Evidence of other disease, metabolic dysfunction, physical examination finding, or
             clinical laboratory finding giving reasonable suspicion of a disease or condition that
             contraindicates use of an investigational drug or patient at high risk from treatment
             complications
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Markus Peck-Radosavljevic, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical University of Vienna</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Universität Wien</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>A-1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2009</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 19, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 19, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 20, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 21, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 21, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 22, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Markus Peck-Radosavljevic, M. D.</name_title>
    <organization>Medizinische Universität Wien</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hepatocellular carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>TACE</keyword>
  <keyword>transarterial chemoembolisation</keyword>
  <keyword>portal hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>angiogenesis</keyword>
  <keyword>VEGF</keyword>
  <keyword>bevacizumab</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

